Niladri S. Chatterji

CONTACT INFORMATION

Department of Computer Science

Stanford University

https://niladri-chatterji.github.io/

niladri@cs.stanford.edu

RESEARCH INTERESTS I am interested in theoretically understanding why current deep learning systems perform well, with an eye on improving them further.

Generalization and Optimization of Overparameterized Models. Many neural network models generalize well despite perfectly fitting noisy training data. I am interested in understanding what leads to successful optimization and generalization.

Robust Deep Learning. Many deep learning models are sensitive shifts in the training distribution. I develop techniques to build robust models.

Sample and Model Size Tradeoffs. Large-scale models are trained on internet-scale data and need to tradeoff between the model size and the number of samples under a compute budget. My focus is to develop a theory to characterize these tradeoffs and to help make training more efficient.

Current

SAIL Postdoctoral Fellow, Stanford University

(June 2021 – Present)

POSITION Advisors: Tatsunori Hashimoto & Percy Liang

EDUCATION

University of California Berkeley

(September 2015 – May 2021)

Ph.D. in Physics Advisor: Peter Bartlett

Thesis: Why do gradient methods work in optimization and sampling?

Indian Institute of Technology Bombay

(August 2010 – May 2015)

Dual Degree (B.Tech. & M.Tech.) in Engineering Physics (Major) and Electrical Engg. (Minor).

AWARDS

Stanford SAIL Postdoctoral Fellowship, 2020

Simons Berkeley Research Fellowship (declined), 2020

Institute Silver Medal, IIT Bombay, 2015

Institute Academic Prize, IIT Bombay, 2012–2014

Work

Research Intern, Google Brain

(Summer 2019)

EXPERIENCE

Advisors: Behnam Neyshabur & Hanie Sedghi

Research Intern, National Research Institute Japan

(Summer 2013)

Advisor: Hisao Nakamura

JOURNAL Papers The interplay between implicit bias and benign overfitting in two-layer linear networks.

Niladri Chatterji, Philip Long, Peter Bartlett.

Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR), 2022.

Foolish crowds support benign overfitting.

Niladri Chatterji, Philip Long.

Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR), 2022.

Oracle lower bounds for sampling algorithms. Niladri Chatterji, Peter Bartlett, Philip Long. Bernoulli, 2022.

Is there an analog of Nesterov acceleration for gradient-based MCMC? Yi-An Ma, Niladri Chatterji, Xiang Cheng, Nicolas Flammarion, Peter Bartlett, Michael Jordan. Bernoulli, 2021.

When does gradient descent with logistic loss find interpolating two-layer networks? Niladri Chatterji, Philip Long, Peter Bartlett. Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR), 2021.

Finite-sample analysis of interpolating linear classifiers in the overparameterized regime. Niladri Chatterji, Philip Long.

Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR), 2021.

Enhancement of spin-transfer torque switching via resonant tunneling Niladri Chatterji, Ashwin Tulapurkar, Bhaskaran Muralidharan. Applied Physics Letters, 2014.

CONFERENCE Papers

Benign overfitting without linearity: Neural network classifiers trained by gradient descent for noisy linear data.

Spencer Frei, Niladri Chatterji, Peter Bartlett. Conference on Learning Theory (COLT), 2022.

Is importance weighting incompatible with interpolating classifiers? Ke Alexander Wang*, Niladri Chatterji*, Saminul Haque, Tatsunori Hashimoto. International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2022.

On the theory of reinforcement learning with once-per-episode feedback. Niladri Chatterji*, Aldo Pacchiano*, Peter Bartlett, Michael Jordan. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2021.

When does gradient descent with logistic loss interpolate using deep networks with smoothed ReLU activations?

Niladri Chatterji, Philip Long, Peter Bartlett. Conference on Learning Theory (COLT), 2021.

OSOM: A simultaneously optimal algorithm for multi-armed and linear contextual bandits. Niladri Chatterji, Vidya Muthukumar, Peter Bartlett.

International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), 2020.

Langevin Monte Carlo without smoothness. Niladri Chatterji*, Jelena Diakonikolas*, Michael Jordan, Peter Bartlett.

International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), 2020.

The intriguing role of module criticality in the generalization of deep networks. Niladri Chatterji, Behnam Neyshabur, Hanie Sedghi.

International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2020. (Spotlight Talk)

Online learning with kernel losses. Niladri Chatterji*, Aldo Pacchiano*, Peter Bartlett. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2019. (Long Talk) Underdamped Langevin MCMC: A non-asymptotic analysis. Xiang Cheng*, Niladri Chatterji*, Peter Bartlett, Michael Jordan. Conference on Learning Theory (COLT), 2018.

On the theory of variance reduction for stochastic gradient Monte Carlo. Niladri Chatterji, Nicolas Flammarion, Yi-An Ma, Peter Bartlett, Michael Jordan. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2018.

Alternating minimization for dictionary learning: Local convergence guarantees. Niladri Chatterji, Peter Bartlett.

Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2017.

PREPRINTS

Understanding scaling laws: Sample and model size tradeoffs in two-layer neural networks. Niladri Chatterji, Percy Liang, Tatsunori Hashimoto. In preparation, 2022.

Deep linear networks can benignly overfit when shallow ones do. Niladri Chatterji, Philip Long. arXiv preprint, 2022. Under review at JMLR.

Undersampling is a minimax optimal robustness intervention in nonparametric classification. Niladri Chatterji*, Saminul Haque*, Tatsunori Hashimoto. arXiv preprint, 2022. Under review.

Random feature amplification: Feature learning and generalization in neural networks. Spencer Frei, Niladri Chatterji, Peter Bartlett. arXiv preprint, 2022. Under review at JMLR.

On the opportunities and risks of foundation models. Rishi Bommasani and Niladri Chatterji et al. arXiv preprint, 2022. Under review at JMLR.

Sharp convergence rates for Langevin dynamics in the nonconvex setting. Xiang Cheng, Niladri Chatterji, Yasin Abbasi Yadkori, Peter Bartlett, Michael Jordan. arXiv preprint, 2018.

THESIS

Why do gradient methods work in optimization and sampling? Niladri Chatterji. Ph.D. Thesis, University of California Berkeley, 2021.

TALKS

Benign overfitting: Beyond the ordinary least squares. *SIAM Mathematics of Data Science*, 2022.

The devil is in the tails and other stories of interpolation. *Simons Institute Deep Learning Theory Workshop and Summer School*, 2022.

Two vignettes about interpolation and generalization. *Stanford Information Systems Laboratory Colloquium*, 2022.

Two vignettes about interpolation and generalization. *Google Algorithms Seminar*, 2022.

Foolish crowds support benign overfitting: lower bounds for sparse interpolators.

Stanford ML Lunch, 2022.

Is importance weighting incompatible with interpolating classifiers? *Stanford ML Lunch*, 2021.

Benign overfitting: Beyond the ordinary least squares. *EPFL ML Reading Group*, 2021.

When does gradient descent find interpolating neural network classifiers? *Harvard Probabilitas Seminar*, 2021.

When does gradient descent find interpolating neural network classifiers? *UCLA Big Data and Machine Learning Seminar*, 2021.

When does gradient descent find interpolating neural network classifiers? *NSF-Simons Mathematics of Deep Learning Journal Club*, 2021.

When does gradient descent find interpolating neural network classifiers? *Conference on Learning Theory*, 2021.

Upper and lower bounds for gradient based sampling methods. *Math Machine Learning Seminar MPI MIS + UCLA*, 2020.

The intriguing role of module criticality in the generalization of deep networks. *Google Brain*, 2019

Analysis of Markov Chain Monte Carlo Algorithms. *Berkeley AI Retreat*, 2019.

Underdamped Langevin Markov chain Monte Carlo. *Simons Institute Industry Day Spotlight*, 2019.

Underdamped Langevin Markov Chain Monte Carlo. *Simons Institute Foundations of Data Science*, 2018.

Underdamped Langevin Markov Chain Monte Carlo. *Midwest Machine Learning Symposium*, 2018.

Alternating minimization for dictionary learning: Local convergence guarantees. *Berkeley AI Seminar*, 2017.

TEACHING Experience

Linear Models (Statistics, UC Berkeley)

Spring 2020

Graduate Student Instructor

Electricity and Magnetism (Physics, UC Berkeley)

Fall 2016, Spring 2017

Graduate Student Instructor

Undergraduate Physics (Physics, UC Berkeley)

Summer 2016, Spring 2016, Fall 2015

Graduate Student Instructor

Basic Electronics Laboratory (Physics, IIT Bombay)

Fall 2014

Teaching Assistant

Electricity and Magnetism (Physics, IIT Bombay)

Spring 2014

Teaching Assistant

Quantum Mechanics (Physics, IIT Bombay)

Fall 2013

Teaching Assistant

Introduction to Numerical Analysis (Mathematics, IIT Bombay)

Summer 2012

Teaching Assistant

STUDENTSMiraç Sügun (Graduate Student)2022MENTOREDApratim Dey (Graduate Student)2022Rohan Taori (Graduate Student)2022Saminul Haque (Graduate Student)2021-22Rohith Kuditipudi (Graduate Student)2021-22Ke Alexander Wang (Graduate Student)2021

SERVICE

Journal Review

Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR), Bernoulli, Annals of Applied Probability, Annales de lÍnstitut Henri Poincaré (B) Probabilités et Statistiques, SIAM Journal on the Mathematics of Data Science.

Conference Review

NeurIPS (2018–), ICML (2020–), COLT (2018–), AISTATS (2019, 2020), ALT (2018, 2021), ICLR (2021), L4DC (2020, 2021).

OTHER Interests

Outside of work, I enjoy biking, hiking, playing soccer, tennis and chess, and baking. Some highlights outside of research include cycling from San Francisco to Los Angeles as part of the AIDS Lifecycle in 2019, and mountaineering expeditions in the Himalayas to Beas Kund (18,000 ft) and Roopkund Lake (15,000 ft).

October 19, 2022